<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Jordan Ristow]]></title><description><![CDATA[The interwebs home of Jordan Ristow]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 11:21:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA["I never saw it coming!"]]></title><description><![CDATA[When we transition from an individual contributor role into managing people or teams, a common mistake people run into is still only being…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/blindsided/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/blindsided/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;When we transition from an individual contributor role into managing people or teams, a common mistake people run into is still only being focused on the immediate problem in front of them. Moving up into management requires expanding that scope of view to encompass what’s immediately here and what could be coming. Starting to think about cause and effect relationships is a crucial skill that often gets overlooked. As humans, our brains like to distort the view we have of previous decisions in order to protect us from feeling unhappy. In order to combat this, we should do a full review of any major decision we have made to see how well our predictions came true. Without measuring this, we cannot say with any accuracy how good a person is at predicting outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do you start to identify possible outcomes and second order effects? A lot of times we have an ideal outcome we want to happen after our decision. “If we execute this project, then this outcome will happen.” So we already have one prediction, now we need to think about others. An easy place to start is to identify the opposite of our ideal outcome. “This project should move the business forward, but what if it doesn’t?” Where does failure of a project or initiative leave the business? Is it in a better position? Or a worse one? Starting to run thought experiments like this will start to open up other potential outcomes. “What if our result is slightly different from what we expect?” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great way to start doing this is by creating a decision journal. Farnam Street has a great article about decision journals &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/2014/02/decision-journal/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; so I won’t go into the specifics of it. Essentially, you write down the situation, what you expect to happen and why and then how you feel about it. As you explore why you think a certain outcome will occur, you can start to identify any built in biases you may have about the situation and decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another useful tool comes from Ray Dalio, in his book Principles, he talks about triangulating your beliefs with believable people. This is where you take your decision, prediction and supporting argument and bounce it off two or three other people you find believable. They can identify blind spots you may have had and even bring up other potential outcomes you may not have thought about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, being an effective manager or leader boils down to how well can you make decisions. Without analyzing the decisions you are making, without having a realistic understanding of possible outcomes, you will have a tough time. Being able to identify and set aside your own biases and take an outsiders view of your decisions will amplify your ability to lead.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Finding Leadership Opportunities]]></title><description><![CDATA[How can you highlight your ability to lead if you aren’t formally in a position of authority? What are some ways to showcase your leadership…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/finding-opportunities/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/finding-opportunities/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;How can you highlight your ability to lead if you aren’t formally in a position of authority? What are some ways to showcase your leadership skillset and potential, without having a title that tells people you are the leader? First, let’s differentiate between a manager and a leader. A lot of people automatically associate managers with leaders, since that is the person they are supposed to follow at work. But not all leaders are going to be managers and not all managers will be good leaders. The best leaders I have worked with and for are the ones who can make a genuine connection with you as a person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you think you are at the point in your career where you want to take on a leadership role, it can seem daunting. How will they know I can handle this extra responsibility? What can I do to “prove” myself to the higher ups? One of the key skills you must have is communication. Be willing to have tough conversations with the people leading you and be able to clearly articulate why you think the way you do. Speaking well is a skill that too few people practice, if you can set yourself apart from the crowd, others will notice. One skill that can help in this area is learning to take a breath before you respond to any comment. Compose your response in your head before speaking it. On this same path, talk to your direct manager about your aspirations. Let them know you think you are ready for a higher level position and get feedback from them. Being able to understand your blind spots is another area to work on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside of communication, remember that as a leader, you are responsible for ensuring things get done. Make sure you are on top of completing your assigned resonsibilities on time. Keep an eye out for team members who may be struggling and see if there is a way you can help them. Being known as the person who will help others get things done, along with getting your own work done, will go a long way to show your ability to lead a group. Doing this without someone asking will show initiative. If you are presented with a situation where an important decision needs to be made, build an argument for why one choice is more optimal than another. Present this to your manager when you go to them. Leading people is a lot of decision making, highlighting your ability to think critically about an issue to determine a path forward is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond just communicating or getting stuff done, look at ways you can reach back and help people who are junior to you. Offer to be a mentor for new employees. Organize informal or formal groups to learn new skills or grow existing skillsets. Find little ways to take initiative. At the end of the day, your title doesn’t matter. True leaders are the ones people look to in a crisis, who is going to remain calm and find a way through it. Showing the ability to do that isn’t tough but it does take extra effort. Ultimately it is that extra effort that will signal to people you have what it takes.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Effectiveness, Efficiency and Measuring Outcomes]]></title><description><![CDATA[Organizations are increasingly more concerned with the effectiveness of their workforces. With increased distractions from e-mail, social…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/measuring-outcomes/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/measuring-outcomes/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Organizations are increasingly more concerned with the effectiveness of their workforces. With increased distractions from e-mail, social media, phone calls, slack and other pop up requirements, there is more scrutiny being placed on how much work employees are actually accomplishing during their work days. Having an understanding what the important things to focus on is vital for everyone in an organization. How can we know if we are working on the most important things?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Effectiveness: doing the right things&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to highlight the “wrong” things to focus on, people have done it all before. Email, slack, texts, social media are all low hanging fruit we should minimize our attention on. However, when it comes to actual work, what is the right thing to focus on? How do we weight all of those tasks we have to take care of? This is where it is vital for organizations to look at expected outcomes for any project or initiative. If you aren’t prioritizing the expected outcomes by impact to the business, it becomes very difficult to identify why one task should be prioritized over another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Efficiency: doing things right&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Efficiency is an easier goal to track. We all spend roughly 8 hours a day at work, how much of that time is spent directly on tasks that move projects or initiatives forward? A “good” answer will depend a lot on your particular role. More reactive roles, where you are waiting for some event to happen before you respond, may have very low direct hours on some days. Knowledge workers may have to spend time researching a topic before they are able to actually take care of a particular task. If you know how to accomplish a task and are simply procrastinating doing it, you are not being efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Measuring outcomes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every organization has a mission statement and some strategic goals. If you don’t know what your orgainzations are, go look them up, ask a manager or coworker what they are. You should keep these in mind and frame the work you do every day within the context of those goals. Look at each of the projects or initiatives you have and see which ones directly align with those goals. Try to identify which outcomes will move the needle the most against any of those strategic goals. Whichever one does that, is where your focus and time should be going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easy to serve platitudes to being effective or efficient in our work. These are becoming buzzwords within business and everyone has their hacks they want to sell you to help make you more effective and efficient. But by simply focusing on those outcomes that drive progress against an organizations strategic goals, you will be more effective.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Finding Our Purpose]]></title><description><![CDATA[Yesterday I wrote a little about how to keep making progress on a goal when we aren’t feeling motivated. One of the strategies I identified…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/why-leadership/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/why-leadership/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I wrote a little about how to keep making progress on a goal when we aren’t feeling motivated. One of the strategies I identified was finding a goal that aligns with our purpose or meaning in life. For the longest time I couldn’t figure out what meaning or purpose I had. Today I wanted to share a little of my experience that helped me to understand and find a true purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve always been an introspective person, looking back on life, reviewing what I’ve done and how I can be a better human. Doing this helps me to understand weaknesses I have as well as allows me to see connections that I missed when I was living through these experiences. When I do this, I tend to break my life up into a few distinct phases and look at what was going on during each phase. Recently I began noticing a common theme that popped up repeatedly during these phases of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;College Life&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was in undergrad, I was searching for that traditional college experience. I wanted to get out, make new friends and go to parties. One day I got an email inviting me to an informational session about a new fraternity that was coming to camus and I checked it out. During the informational session, I found out this fraternity did not have a chapter on campus and I would be helping to build it from the ground up. If I joined, I would be on the ground floor shaping the organization from day one. I was hooked immediately. While we worked through the chartering process, it was not smooth sailing. We hit numerous roadblocks and had a lot of stalled progress. Eventually, I was handed ownership of the chartering process and was told to have the paperwork completed in six months. With a lot of help, I was able to meet the deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Early Career&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first job out of undergrad was working as a project manager/project engineer in a government office. There were a lot of problems in this office, people who had worked together for years and allowed old grudges to fester. There were times I would overhear people shouting at each other on the phone. It was an unpleasant place to work. But, because I was new and didn’t have all of these previous experiences biasing my actions, I was able to get work done. People soon started turning to me to help interface between different offices. The acqusitions people would call me and ask me to help one of the engineers clarify his documents. Other project managers would ask me how to approach the acquisitions people without starting a fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Mid Career&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After my time as a project manager, I accepted a position managing a small department at a new location. This role would be my first true leadership role but I would soon realize it wasn’t just going to be a simple management gig. When I showed up, the organization was going through a massive IT system upgrade that required changing a lot of old business processes. Further, they hadn’t completed the requirements of a previous reorganization effort, leaving them with a lot of duplicated work. I spent my first year simply trying to understand what, exactly, my department was supposed to be doing. After three years, I had managed to streamline a lot of our processes and align other departments with their intended purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Finding the Common Theme&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With hindsight, it’s easy to connect threads that run through our lives. We can build up an image of ourselves in the moment that doesn’t accurately reflect who we truly are. Throughout my life I have never seen myself as an exceptional leader. I tend to be more of a quiet person, focusing on the work I need to get done in my own life. After looking back through these different phases of my life, I realized that leadership is something I value and am good at. I want to start sharing lessons on leadership with more people, identifying how they can use it to improve their own lives.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Are You Motivated or Dedicated?]]></title><description><![CDATA[For the longest time I’ve told myself I will start my own side hustle eventually. I would sit down, plan out what I wanted to do and get…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/motivation-or-dedication/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/motivation-or-dedication/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;For the longest time I’ve told myself I will start my own side hustle eventually. I would sit down, plan out what I wanted to do and get started. For a little while, I would be motivated to stick with it and make progress on it daily. Then something would happen. Someone would invite me to go do something. I wouldn’t be feeling well. And I would miss a day. Then it would be a few days. Eventually I would realize it had been a few months since I did anything with that project and whatever inspiration I had initially would be long gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am willing to bet most people reading this have some similar story. How can we fight this battle? There are a few strategies that I have found so far, none of them are perfect. There’s the old school, just force yourself to grind strategy. This is where you make yourself do whatever it is you need to do, for me this would be writing.  The downside to this strategy is that eventually, you may start viewing this side project as a negative thing in your life. It can become a weight that drags you down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another strategy is looking at your side hustle and finding meaning or purpose within it. A lot of people pursue a side hustle to bring in some extra money, but also as an escape from a day job they may not enjoy. If you can align your side hustle with a sense of purpose in your life, that can overcome any lack of motivation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, you can leverage those times when you are feeling motivated or inspired and use them to build a system that sets you up for success when you are lacking the motivation. If you are creating content as a side hustle, planning out the topics for your content in advance or building layouts of post ideas would be one possible system. Writing multiple posts on one day to build up a buffer for those days when life happens and you can’t sit down to take care of business. All sorts of little tricks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, this time around, I am combining strategies two and three to help keep me moving forward on this. I’ve challenged myself to get a post up each day in October. So far I have made it happen. When I have motivation and inspiration, I am writing down a list of topics I want to cover, building some skeletion posts that I can go fill in later when I don’t have anything else. And I have a topic that keeps me interested and pushing forward. Join me in the journey.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Building Effective Organizations]]></title><description><![CDATA[One of the programgs I worked to implement while with the Air Force was an employee performance management program. A lot of companies are…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/building-effective-organizations/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/building-effective-organizations/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;One of the programgs I worked to implement while with the Air Force was an employee performance management program. A lot of companies are moving to this type of model, as it allows employees and managers to be on the same page about expectations. Further, it makes it easier for individual contributors to understand how their role creates value for the overall organization. At first, I thought this program was just adding a lot of extra hoops we had to jump through to evaluate employees performance. Instead of being able to just check a box to say whether the employee was doing their job or not, we had to build out specific plans identifying our expectations for each employee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After implementing this system, I gained an appreciation and understanding of the value it can create. If managers and leaders don’t clearly lay out what is expected of contributors, if those contributors do not know how their work aligns with the organizations overall goals and objectives, there can be a disconnect with the individuals. How can a person know what is important to work on, if they don’t know what work of theirs is important to the organization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your company doesn’t have a performance management system set up, or your manager doesn’t effectively utilize the one in place, sit down with them and have a conversation. Especially if you feel disengaged at work. Remember in school, the professors would provide a syllabus at the beginning of each semester, identify what work you were responsible for and how it would be assessed? This made it really easy for you to know where you were missing the mark and why. Performance management can be your syllabus in the professional world. Having these conversations ensures everyone is on the same page when it comes to performance and development. Managers won’t be blindsided by someone leaving their team, they will have a better understanding of when a person believes they are ready for a new role with more responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Own Your Career]]></title><description><![CDATA[I’m trying to avoid writing a million “I listened to a CEO talk and learned this” articles, but sometimes you hear something that sticks…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/career-framing/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/career-framing/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m trying to avoid writing a million “I listened to a CEO talk and learned this” articles, but sometimes you hear something that sticks with you and you just have to share it. When I heard this CEO speak earlier this week, she covered a lot of ideas some of which I was able to write down, others have just been coming back to me over the past few days. One of the ones that surfaced recently was something along the lines of owning and defining what your career story is. In her case, she realized early on most of her positions had been customer interfacing. So she totally owned it and branded herself as the customer expert in her company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was really interesting to me as I have had a lot of trouble really telling the story of my own career, both as an internal dialog and on my resume. Our internal dialog is such a powerful force, yet so many people use it negatively. “I’m just a customer service representative.” Or “I only manage the projects.” Both of these can be reframed to show how you enable the customer to be successful. “I take care of any issues our customers have with the product.” Or “I work closely with customers to define their business problem and develop a solution to it.” Changing that internal narrative can help us see how we can be of service to others through our role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, when we have a clear definition of what we do and how we create value, we can easily explain why a role is a good fit for us. For me personally, this has definitely been something I have struggled with as I worked to grow my career. Early on, I simply saw myself as a project manager so I would highlight my project management skillset. But one of the key things I was missing is that as a project manager, I was the interface to our customer. I worked closely with them to understand their problems, I was the bridge between them and the technical team. Because I didn’t frame my experience in this way, it was difficult to understand how managing construction projects could translate into managing the project lifecycle of a new consumer electronic product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you move into a leadership or management role, being able to do this also becomes necessary in order to build a cohesive team. When you can clearly articulate what value your team is creating or how they are creating positive outcomes for the organization or for others, you can start to see them buy into the work you are asking them to do. When I was building up the facility condition analytics function at my last position, I had to become an evangelist and preach to everyone how beneficial this change was going to be. How it was going to help our customers, how it was going to help other teams we worked with. As I did this, I could see everyone starting to buy in and we made a lot of progress with pushing these changes to the entire organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next time you are starting to question your work role, or have that negative internal dialog about your position, see if you can reframe what you do. Try to identify how you are being of service to others and see if that helps you gain perspective. Thanks for reading and if this resonated with you please connect with me!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Be Willing to Bet on Yourself]]></title><description><![CDATA[I was offered my first management job at 29 after 5 years of managing projects. I’ll be the first to admit, I wasn’t the greatest project…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/bet-on-yourself/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/bet-on-yourself/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I was offered my first management job at 29 after 5 years of managing projects. I’ll be the first to admit, I wasn’t the greatest project manager but I was effective in getting work done. I knew how to effectively leverage all members of a team to ensure a project was successful. I thought I was ready to go be a kick ass manager and prove to other people they were wrong to doubt my abilities. I remember the day the offer came in, I had left work early to go take a test for a class I was taking, Foundations of Mathematical Proofs (yes I am that person who takes math courses for fun). When I saw the email the next morning, I was shocked. Here was the opportunity I had been waiting for. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward a few months after I showed up and started, I was totally unprepared for the shift in responsbilities. As a project manager, I was used to having well defined and measurable daily/weekly/monthly goals I had to meet. This new world of efficiently managing resources assigned to me was so foreign. The breadth of everything I was responsible for was incredibly overwhelming. I had no idea what I was doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two years later, I was recognized as the Davis-Monthan AFB Senior Civilian of the Year, an award given to the most impactful civilian on the installation for a given year. Going from an overwhelmed slacker to an overly ambitious high achiever was a great transformation. I am not solely responsible for these achievements, there were a lot of external factors that helped, from an incredibly supportive boss to the incredibly talented teams I was lucky to work with. But there was also a big internal shift within myself that helped me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning how to lead, learning how to build lasting relationships and learning to understand an organizations mission statement are all key skills I had to pick up. Throughout this journey, I gained a deeper understanding of my own inherent strengths and weaknesses and I am attempting to document some of these here. Some day I will write those stories down and share the lessons. Today I just wanted to highlight the power of betting on yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are willing to take a big risk based solely on your own belief in yourself, you are creating an opportunity for massive success. In most cases, even if you fail, the experience you will have gained puts you so far ahead of where you would have been, it becomes a win anyway. What is something you are afraid of doing right now? Why don’t you use that fear as a signal of what you should be moving towards?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A Conversation with Heather Brunner, WPEngine CEO]]></title><description><![CDATA[Last night I ventured out to my first networking event here in Austin. Normally I’m not one to enjoy these, like most other people, because…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/wpengine-ceo-talk/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/wpengine-ceo-talk/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Last night I ventured out to my first networking event here in Austin. Normally I’m not one to enjoy these, like most other people, because everything feels so transactional. But this event, Meet ATX, sounded like it may be a little different. Instead of the normal meet people, have drinks, maybe exchange info and then go home, the organizers have set up guided conversations with some of Austins’ business leaders. Last night we heard from Heath Brunner, the CEO of WPEngine. Overall, I think the event was valuable and I plan on going back when they host more. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;If you dont ask, the answer is always no.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the biggest takeaway I had from listening to Heather is the power of simply asking for what you want. As she was telling her story and answering questions, this theme kept popping up. She mentioned several times where she got a position simply because she had asked for more responsbility or asked to learn a new skill. The people she had talked to remembered her asking and brought opportunities to her. If no one knows what you want, how can you expect to get it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;It’s all about the relationships.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was interesting to hear another common theme that continued to pop up throughout her talk: building good relationships. During her career, she had the opportunity to meet and build relationships with people who would continue to support her. The timing of hearing this was pretty powerful, since I have been reflecting on what helped me to be successful and realizing it was always key relationships. It is just a reminder that when you build authentic relationships, they can magnify your ability to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Karma is powerful.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This point was something that I have believed in for a while. Whether you call it karma or something else, the idea that if you put good out into the world, you will be repaid is incredibly powerful. Hearing someone who has had great success remind me of this was encouraging. It encouraged me to continue writing down what I have learned from my experiences and putting it out into the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5 Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most powerful things I took away from Heather is actually a set of questions she said she asks herself continuously:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Am I growing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Am I learning?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Am I having fun?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does my manager have my back?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I have a plan for the future?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are powerful questions that can help anyone. Especially those people who are feeling unfulfilled in their careers. The first three are great “compass” questions to help you know if what you are doing currently aligns with who you are as a person. The last one is one that people often overlook, we get bogged down in the day to day stresses and don’t look at where our current path is taking us. The fourth one is especially powerful when you are questioning what you are currently doing. In my experience, most of the times when I haven’t enjoyed a job it stemmed from a feeling of the manager not being invested in me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a lot more she covered but I was focused on listening and trying to take it all in so I didn’t write down any more notes. If you have the opportunity to go listen to any leader talk, I would definitely suggest you take it. If you’re in Austin, I believe they host these Meet ATX events the first Tuesday of every month. Come check it out and say hi if you do!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Let's Talk About Risk, Baby]]></title><description><![CDATA[Over the first few years of my career, I learned about managing risk within a portfolio. For me, specifically, that risk came in the form of…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/risky-business/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/risky-business/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Over the first few years of my career, I learned about managing risk within a portfolio. For me, specifically, that risk came in the form of catastrophic infrastructure failure. The air conditioning system in our server building going down, a concrete slab in the middle of the runway crumbling into pieces as planes take off and land or the electrical substation overloading causing an entire installation to be without power for an extended period of time. When this is the world you are immersed in, your brain starts to view things differently from people. I am constantly weighing the benefits of one action versus another action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What does this mean for me, Jordan?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thats a great question. Whether in your personal life or professional, weighing the risks you are taking is a critical aspect of thriving. Identifying the total overall risk across an entire portfolio allows us to make better informed decisions to guide our lives. I’m sure everyone has heard of the phrase, death by a thousand paper cuts. This is what can happen when total risk isn’t weighed when choosing to pursue some new initiative. Companies are littered with abandoned projects that seemed like a great idea at the time but quickly became resource drains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Okay, but what portfolio are you talking about here?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, a portfolio can be considered any collection of things. Typically, in businesses, portfolios are made up of programs and projects. An example from my own life, my previous employer had an environmental portfolio which was composed of air quality and water quality management programs, as well as environmental restoration projects. In a personal life, the easiest example would be a personal finance portfolio, comprised of any income you earn, long term debt, short term debt and investments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So, how do I apply risk management?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be a tricky question to answer, so I am going to do my best to simplify it down to a few basic concepts. First, never make a decision in isolation. I remember in my engineering classes we always got to work with isolated systems. It made the calculations easier but we never get to deal with isolated systems in the real world. There is always external forces applying pressures to any system. As a real life example of this, lets look at personal finances. It’s easy to look at isolated expenses and think they aren’t that bad, $10 for Netflix sounds cheap, so does $15 for HBONow and of course everyone needs to be more mindful so we need Headspace at $13. Oh and we have to have a SoulCycle membership. Pretty soon, we’ve created a $300 bill every month from all of these insignificant expenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, identify what your priorities are and eliminate anything not tied to those priorities. For a real world example of this, my last job was to build out a comprehensive list of every facility or infrastructure requirement the installation had. Every. Single. One. It was a long list and there would never be enough resources to meet every requirement. But, we knew what our priorities were. So having this list allowed us to analyze our entire portfolio and align our resource allocation with the organizations priorities. Our main missin was to launch airplanes, so any requirement that enabled us to do that was at the top of our list. Anything not directly enabling that mission was pushed to the bottom. This is ruthless and it doesn’t make you any friends but it is necessary to ensure the survival of any organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take anything away from this, I hope it is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t make decisions in isolation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clearly identify your priorities and align decisions with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gathering Effectively]]></title><description><![CDATA[I am vehemently anti-meetings. Early on in my career I had seen my fair share of terrible meetings that should have been an email. Or ones…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/effective-gathering/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/effective-gathering/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I am vehemently anti-meetings. Early on in my career I had seen my fair share of terrible meetings that should have been an email. Or ones intended to provide quick project updates that quickly devolved into someone venting about their projects. This experience shaped my disdain for meetings and I promised myself I would never host meetings like these when I was in charge. Fast-forward to when I finally was in charge of my own teams. For the first year, I didn’t hold a central staff meeting. I had each team lead attend the weekly Operations meeting to get the important information, which they could then pass down to their teams. This worked for a bit, but eventually I needed to get consistent flow of information back from each team. Trying to catch the leads and get updates on the fly was no longer working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So eventually I gave in and started having a weekly staff meeting, where the team leads would provide me with updates, I would pass down any important directions and we would hash out any issues that teams were having. I was still kind of anti-meeting though, so even these meetings were not as effective as they could be. I focused too much on minimizing the disruption to peoples days and tended to run through the meetings too quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Wouldn’t it be great if we could have productive meetings that don’t suck?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With my utter contempt for meetings, I was intrigued when I ran across a book recently, &lt;em&gt;The Art of Gathering&lt;/em&gt;, by Priya Parker. She promiesd to transform terrible meetings into wondrous occasions for celebration. Okay not quite that far, but she did mention making them suck just a little bit less. So I was hooked. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She covers a lot of ground in the book and I’m not going to give you the cliff’s notes here, but the key takeaway I had is that meetings tend to suck because nobody takes ownership of them. Nobody takes the necessary time to sit down and create a meeting with intent and purpose. We hold a weekly staff meeting to get everyone in the same room. The manager doesn’t have anything to discuss. The team members don’t want to bring up any of their concerns in front of a crowd. Somehow, we end up filling the allotted time anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I read this book, I have a few action items I need to implement. While I am not in a position of calling meetings anymore, I do get invited to meetings. For these meetings, I plan on ensuring I walk in prepared to discuss whatever the topic is. For those of you who do set up meetings, I would highly recommend picking up a copy of the book and taking some notes.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Driving Success]]></title><description><![CDATA[Random Thoughts on SuccessAfter this past week, I’ve been reflecting a little on what has driven my previous success. One of the key themes…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/drive-success/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/drive-success/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h3&gt;Random Thoughts on Success&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this past week, I’ve been reflecting a little on what has driven my previous success. One of the key themes I keep noticing and coming back to is the relationship factor. Anytime I have been able to create great wins for the organization I was working for, I had to leverage skillsets from a lot of different people. This is typical in the modern business world, who isn’t a part of at least one work team?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the difference, from my experience, has been the nature of the relationships I had with the members of that team. From my first days as a project engineer, I was exposed to team leaders who tried to force their will on different members of the team. This was not the most effective strategy. The biggest thing I learned from these early days, we need to build relationships based on mutual respect to drive effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a more seasoned project manager, I had colleagues with several more years of experience coming to me to ask my advice on how to move projects forward. The advice I gave them was simple, know your job and don’t tell someone else how to do their job. Ask “how do we make this happen” instead of demanding something be done. When you approach a person on a human level, respecting the fact that they probably know more than you do about that job function, they will move mountains to help you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It amazes me, to this day, how many people don’t understand this concept.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Building Effective Teams]]></title><description><![CDATA[How do we build more effective teams in an organization?As a leader/manager in an organization, it is crucial to create highly effective…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/effective-teams/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/effective-teams/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h3&gt;How do we build more effective teams in an organization?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a leader/manager in an organization, it is crucial to create highly effective teams. When a team coalesces around a central vision, they can magnify the effectiveness of the individual contributors. But how do leaders create this buy in? Shouldn’t people give everything they can because we are giving them a paycheck? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Relationships based on authentic connections are key.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When your team’s only motivation is a paycheck, you create a transactional relationship, where they are only as invested as they need to be to get their payoff. If you instead focus on building a relationship based on mutual respect, that person is more willing to go the extra mile for you. When each member of your team is willing to go above and beyond, that is when you create the most value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Create a bold vision, then create buy in.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Defining a bold guiding vision for your team is an often over looked step in building high functioning teams. If you, as the manager, can define the direction you are going and then build excitement around that vision, it makes the team feel more connected to their work. Without some guiding vision, a team will wander aimlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy for managers to get bogged down in the day to day drudgery of keeping a system moving. Meetings, phone calls, interviews all suck time and energy away from what their core focus should be. But it is crucial to take time to define the overall vision for a team and build consensus around that. If a manager fails to do this, they are losing out.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Be Strategic in Your Career Choices]]></title><description><![CDATA[So recently I was having a conversation with someone about work and career progression and they made a comment that got me thinking. They…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/career-strategy/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/career-strategy/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;So recently I was having a conversation with someone about work and career progression and they made a comment that got me thinking. They said &lt;em&gt;“You don’t need to worry about your career, you just need to worry about finding the next position. Your career will develop later.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some context, my current role isn’t permanently assigned to a single team, and they were referring to me landing a permanent spot on a team. But zooming out a little, there are a few things we can explore with this statement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the initial positions we take in our careers can drastically shape what future positions are available to us. In software engineering, if you start out focused solely on frontend work it can be difficult to transition into a backend position after that. Or if you go into a specialized role like DevOps, you may be pigeonholed the rest of your career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, focusing solely on landing that next position without considering what our ultimate career goals are, is short sighted. If we want to become a CTO, it doesn’t make sense to work on becoming the most technically smart engineer. We need to branch out into managing teams and learning how to shape and steer the strategy of our company. Conversely, if we want to move into a lead technical role, architecting the systems and deployment strategies it doesn’t make sense to get into management positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everyone is going to know what they want to end up as in their career and thats okay. Some people are totally happy just moving from one job to another without worrying about achieving some end goal. But a lot of people are unhappy with their jobs and often it boils down to them not doing what they feel like they want to do. Often, they can’t tell you exactly why they got into their current position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we don’t have some long term vision for our career, we cannot complain when we end up somewhere we don’t want to be.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Step One: Diagnosis]]></title><description><![CDATA[Good strategy is built on an underlying structure that anyone can use in their own life. We can generalize three distinct phases in…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/identify-the-problem/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/identify-the-problem/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Good strategy is built on an underlying structure that anyone can use in their own life. We can generalize three distinct phases in strategic thinking and then build a process we follow. Typically, these phases can be identified as diagnosis, guiding policy and action plans. Today we are going to focus on the diagnosis portion. How do we go about diagnosing a situation? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly identifying our current position is the key motivator during diagnosis. In military strategy this is when the scouts are out finding the enemies locations, watching their movements and identifying key parts of the battlefield. In life, this would be the time spent assessing what your current situation is. What does your career look like? What do your relationships look like? What is the general direction you are headed? Asking yourself these and other similar questions will help you diagnose the current state of your battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is a good tool to use during diagnosis?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since diagnosis is all about gathering information and building out your “map of the territory”, the most effective and simplest tool available to us are questions. A lot of times, we avoid asking questions because we worry that we will appear incompetent. We worry people will question why we are in our position if we have to ask all these questions. In reality, we all have blind spots and asking questions is the easiest way to minimize our blind spots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;“When you become a leader your job is to define the problem. Not solve it”&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, during diagnosis the goal is to identify the current state of things. As we explore the current state, the possibility for emotional reactions to what we discover exists. We need to focus solely on gathering the information during this stage and not jumping into some action based on our emotions. Expanding our understanding will allow us to build a plan to move us closer to where we want to be.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Alright, What Exactly is Strategic Thinking?]]></title><description><![CDATA[Strategy: a high level plan to achieve one or more goals under conditions of uncertaintity. —WikipediaIn life, we often set goals for…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/what-is-strategy/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/what-is-strategy/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h3&gt;Strategy: a high level plan to achieve one or more goals under conditions of uncertaintity. —Wikipedia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In life, we often set goals for ourselves, or we build out a vision for how we want situations to play out. We tend to look towards the future and see ourselves in certain situations. But how do we get from where we are today, to those future situations? For most people, we just kind of hope that we will end up there. But there are people who actually sit down and look at ways to potentially reach those endpoints. This is the heart of strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dictionary definition of strategy: The science and art of using all the forces of a nation to execute approved plans as effectively as possible during peace or war.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people tend to relate strategy immediately to military strategy, which is where the word originated from. The Greek origins of strategy directly translate to the art of troop leader or general. But strategic thinking has proven useful beyond the battle field, as we can see with the increase in Strategic Planning teams within large business organizations. While these may seem like totally unrelated areas, both military and businesses must deal with limited resources, constantly changing landscapes and contending with outside entities that are actively trying to outmaneuver them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, boiling all of these definitions down to a straight forward explanation: strategy is the overarching vision we have in place to get to “desirable ends with available means”. Strategy is not the individual steps we need to take to get to these ends, those are tactics. Strategy tends to focus more on the what than the how. Now that we have the basics of what strategy is, we can start exploring how to apply it in different life situations. Check back later this week for the next installment!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Strategy Project]]></title><description><![CDATA[For anyone who has been following me, you have seen the series I was doing on Naval Ravikants tweetstorm on how to create wealth. I got up…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/strategy-project/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/strategy-project/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;For anyone who has been following me, you have seen the series I was doing on Naval Ravikants tweetstorm on how to create wealth. I got up to his post on how the internet has enabled people to scale their niche obsession and reach thousands of people with similar interests and it got me thinking on how I can better leverage what I am doing with my website. One topic that has been very interesting to me lately has been strategy and how people can use it in their life and careers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Where did all of this strategy talk come from Jordan?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my previous work position, I was put in charge of 30 people across three teams. I had no idea what to do or how to manage the chaos I had been dropped into. My first six months were a blur of reading everything I could find on what the goal of the department was as well as how to manage people. It was a similar situation to the one Shane Parrish from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fs.blog&quot;&gt;fs.blog&lt;/a&gt; wrote about &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/smart-decisions/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I needed to learn about setting the vision for a whole department, along with ensuring that vision lined up with the overall vision of the organization. It was a tough spot to be in for someone who never planned to be in that position from the beginning (more on this in a future post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thats the short version of what got me invested in learning strategic thinking and planning. After that initial shockwave, I realized this thinking could be applied to a lot of other areas in life and I started exploring different ways to apply it. It also led me to start reading everything I could find on strategy, including topics on game theory and old war strategy books. And now, after feeling lost with how to direct this website, I plan on presenting this information to you readers. If there are any topics you want to learn about, please reach out and let me know.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Give Society What It Doesn't Know How To Get -- My Thoughts]]></title><description><![CDATA[Earlier this year @naval posted a long tweetstorm about how to get rich without getting lucky, which blew up. Since then he has posted a…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/give-society-what-it-wants/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/give-society-what-it-wants/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Earlier this year &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/naval&quot;&gt;@naval&lt;/a&gt; posted a long tweetstorm about how to get rich without getting lucky, which blew up. Since then he has posted a series of podcasts expounding on each individual tweet (view it &lt;a href=&quot;https://nav.al/how-to-get-rich#more-28492840&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Each of these posts provided a more in depth look at what he meant. In this series of posts I will summarize what each podcast covers and write out some actionable take aways I plan on implementing from that particular conversation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Give Society What it Doesn’t Know how to Get — at scale&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When working to create massive wealth, it is the people and companies that identify what society wants and can deliver that to society at scale that will win. When we think about some of today’s most successful companies, we see a similar pattern. Apple perfected the smartphone and then made it accessible to billions of people. Google made the worlds information available to everyone, not just the people who could afford to buy lots of books. Uber brought the world of private car services to the masses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common thread among these companies is that the original product was once seen as a luxury that only rich people could afford. These companies came along and made that luxury available to the masses and it so doing, created vast wealth for their shareholders. Some cases, the companies invented an entirely new category that people had not thought of before. Others were an evolution with some defining characteristic that set them apart. In either case, it was opening up the availability that helped propel the wealth creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Key Takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure out what product you can provide and then figure out how to scale it.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Live Below Your Means -- My Thoughts]]></title><description><![CDATA[Earlier this year @naval posted a long tweetstorm about how to get rich without getting lucky, which blew up. Since then he has posted a…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/live-below-your-means/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/live-below-your-means/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Earlier this year &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/naval&quot;&gt;@naval&lt;/a&gt; posted a long tweetstorm about how to get rich without getting lucky, which blew up. Since then he has posted a series of podcasts expounding on each individual tweet (view it &lt;a href=&quot;https://nav.al/how-to-get-rich#more-28492840&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Each of these posts provided a more in depth look at what he meant. In this series of posts I will summarize what each podcast covers and write out some actionable take aways I plan on implementing from that particular conversation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The most dangerous things are heroin and a monthly salary.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post has a few things going on in it. Starting out, he talks about lifestyle upgrades and how people tend to upgrade their lifestyles too quickly. We get a raise at work and immediately look for how we can improve our life with that money. Usually, the thing that would improve our lives most, gets overlooked, and that is buying back part of your freedom. Instead, we look at upgrading the car or house. This happens slowly and we don’t really notice the changes while we are making them. But then one day, we’re making $100 an hour and still have no money left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably the easiest trap we can fall into that prevents us from building true wealth. I know I am guilty of it, I  wound up buying three new cars in succession when I was younger. Each one a worse decision than the previous one. Luckily I have started moving past this behavior, but I still find myself wanting to upgrade my life as I grow in my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing he points out, that I had never thought about, is the ideal way to make a lot of money. If we slowly build up to a very high hourly rate, we still have a hard time accumulating money. However, if we were to instead have some immediate windfall, we wouldn’t have the problem of lifestyle creep. Obviously, we would want to make sure not to spend all of the money we just made, but making these discrete chunks of money usually leaves us better off than slow and steady buildups of hourly wage gains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Key Takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this post, I really want to focus on finding ways to just make discrete chunks of money instead of building up my hourly rate.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Just Do The Work]]></title><description><![CDATA[I often find myself wanting to write. I’ll be at home, at work or out and about and thing to myself “I really want to just sit down and…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/do-the-work/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/do-the-work/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I often find myself wanting to write. I’ll be at home, at work or out and about and thing to myself “I really want to just sit down and write for a bit.” But then I find all sorts of little things to do to avoid writing. Checking Instagram or Twitter. Messing with my LinkedIn profile. Washing the dishes (weird I know). Literally anything to keep from sitting down in front of the computer to actually write something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some times, I do get writers block. So I honestly can’t think of the words I want to say when I sit down. This happens to everyone and is completely normal. Usually though, if I force myself to sit there I will start throwing out random thoughts and eventually coalesce into some semi-coherent rambling. This is, from what I hear, the normal writing process for a lot of people. But in these cases, I forced myself to show up and do the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many of us do similar things with other parts of our lives? Wanting a relationship, wanting to get fit, wanting to eat better. We do everything else, saying eventually we’ll get to that hard thing we really want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently got myself back in the gym and on a regular workout program, which got me thinking about this topic. I didn’t make any excuses for not going to the gym, but once I got back in, I kept wanting to quit the workout halfway through. But that wouldn’t have given me any progress or satisfaction. So I did the work and I am seeing the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This experience reminded me of what I have long known, but tend to forget. We just need to do the work. Instead of putting it off or making excuses or trying to hack our way around the work, just do it. Suck up the short term pain and get it over with. The payoff is always worth the work you have to do.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[You Won't Get Rich Renting Out Your Time -- My Thoughts]]></title><description><![CDATA[Earlier this year @naval posted a long tweetstorm about how to get rich without getting lucky, which blew up. Since then he has posted a…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/renting-out-your-time/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/renting-out-your-time/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Earlier this year &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/naval&quot;&gt;@naval&lt;/a&gt; posted a long tweetstorm about how to get rich without getting lucky, which blew up. Since then he has posted a series of podcasts expounding on each individual tweet (view it &lt;a href=&quot;https://nav.al/how-to-get-rich#more-28492840&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Each of these posts provided a more in depth look at what he meant. In this series of posts I will summarize what each podcast covers and write out some actionable take aways I plan on implementing from that particular conversation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuing my exploration of Naval’s thread on how to create wealth, let’s explore his thoughts on renting out your time, aka working for someone else. One of the key things he highlights about working for someone else, is that your compensation is tied directly to your inputs. Every hour you are there, you get some compensation, and no matter how much that hourly compensation is, you only earn it when you show up. Your job won’t pay you while you sleep. It won’t pay you if you take an extended leave of absence. In order to make money during times you aren’t being productive, you have to own a piece of the business. This way, anytime the company makes money, you are making money as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digging a little deeper into inputs vs outputs, it starts to become clear that we need to find an area where our outputs scale non-linearly from our inputs. Creating content, building a digital platform for people to use, creating other software systems. These all scale non-linearly. Your book can reach potentially millions of people, but you don’t have to do any extra work for it to go from one person to a million. This is where his point about mismatched inputs/outputs really comes into play. Even this post, could potentially reach a large audience for just an hour of my time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A final thing to highlight, he points out that when you rent out your time, you are replaceable. You may be really good at whatever your job is, but there is always someone else who would be willing to do that work. Maybe even at a cheaper price than they are paying you. So it’s really easy to get replaced when you are working for someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Action Items&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading through his post/thoughts about this, it has given me even more motivation to continue investing in companies and work on pursuing my own opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Making Better Decisions with a Radically Open Mind]]></title><description><![CDATA[How do we make better decisions? What are the biggest hindrances people face when trying to make decisions? In regular life as well as…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/radical-open-mind/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/radical-open-mind/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;How do we make better decisions? What are the biggest hindrances people face when trying to make decisions? In regular life as well as business, it is often viewed that whoever can make the fastest decision will win the situations. In reality, it is whoever makes the best decision quickly who often winds up winning. But what goes into making a better decision? Most companies don’t put time into training their people on how to make better decisions. Most people just go about it the best they can. Stumbling through life making the most optimal decisions they know how. But usually these decisions aren’t the true optimal decision. Our brains have a lot of subliminal ways to hide things we aren’t strong in to protect our ego. We are terrible at recognizing what our blind spots are and this leads us to overconfidence in predicting outcomes of our decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Well cool Jordan, thanks for completely destroying my fragile mental state already. Do you have any advice on how to get better at this?” -Anyone reading this, probably. Maybe.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decision making is a very complex process. We take in information, analyze it, make predictions about trends we may see and then use all of that to come to some conclusion. A lot of discussion around decision making focuses on the analysis and prediction portions of this process. Every article out there talking about mental models is really focused on ways to analyze and predict. But what happens if the information supporting that analysis isn’t 100% accurate? How do we know we have good information to begin with? Any analysis or prediction based on faulty information is going to fail, no matter how good the techniques used to make it. How can we dial in on the truth when we seek out information? One promising place to start is with radical open-mindedness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Radical open-mindedness is a concept Ray Dalio explores a lot in his book Principles. Essentially, it boils down to opening ourselves up to being wrong. Welcoming disagreements as a pursuit of finding out what is true, instead of viewing them as fights to be won. Suspending our ego and accepting that we will not always have the correct answer and that is okay. Focusing on achieving our goal instead of looking good by always having the answer. Finally, reaching out to different experts and having them explain opposing viewpoints to you from their perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ego and Blind Spots: The Twin Pillars of Terrible Decision Making&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our biggest obstacle in drilling down into what is true, tends to be ourselves. I know, shocking. We’re all amazing thinkers and see things clearly all of the time. Not. Our brains are very good at protecting our ego. Ego, everyone has one but no one wants to admit it. It is that part of us that experiences and reacts to the outside world. It is the part of us that gets bruised when we find out we are wrong. What causes us to cling to ideas, even when we have seen they are incorrect. The ego prevents us from recognizing our blind spots, those areas where we don’t know as much as we think we know. These two combined, ego and blind spots, are our two greatest barriers to finding out what is true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite quotes in this area comes from Ray Dalio. He says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Replace your attachment to being right with the joy of learning what’s true.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have found this to be a strong guiding light in my own quest for better decisions. Anytime we feel upset during a discussion, we should take a step back and recognize, it is probably stemming from our ego trying to protect us from being hurt. During these moments we need to fight to suspend our ego and accept that maybe you are actually wrong. A lot of times we get caught up in trying to look good, by having the correct answer, but if we don’t actually have the correct answer, we wind up looking bad. We need to shift our focus to simply achieving our goal, and accepting that maybe this time we don’t have the correct answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am still in the process of being radically open-minded, working to suspend my ego and approach situations assuming I am wrong. I am constantly battling old tendencies of assuming I am the smartest person at the table. But I am making progress on it. Share with me your progress on suspending your ego!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A Brief Catch Up & Currently Reading]]></title><description><![CDATA[Howdy, y’all!So, June and July have been some hectic months. I moved to Texas, started a new job and have been slowly getting settled in and…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/currently-reading/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/currently-reading/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h3&gt;Howdy, y’all!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, June and July have been some hectic months. I moved to Texas, started a new job and have been slowly getting settled in and exploring my new city. This has kind of put a damper on my energy and focus to write and put out new content. But, I am starting to feel more settled, so I plan on starting to make more time for writing and creating new content for the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of this, I want to start highlighting some of the items I read each week that really open my eyes. You know, another generic weekly roundup type of blog post. However, I plan on including not only articles, but also books that I am reading and some background information on those books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also plan on shifting the focus of the blog from the random software development/personal finance focus I have had to more of a critical thinking/decision analysis focus. I have been reading a lot in both of these areas lately and want to start writing things about them to help myself remember the topics, and if my writing benefits someone else out there then thats even better!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, enough catch up let’s talk about what I’ve been reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Blogs&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/&quot;&gt;Collaborative Fund&lt;/a&gt;:
So this first one isn’t a particular post, but the overall blog over at Collaborative Fund always has some really interesting articles. Mostly focused on finance, but theres some good gems about overall decision making included.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.calculatedriskblog.com/&quot;&gt;Calculated Risk&lt;/a&gt;:
I actually found this blog from Collaborative Fund, but it has a lot of really interesting economic data commentary. Not quite focused on decision making, but any decision requires facts to help guide it and he provides some incredible fact based analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nav.al/how-to-get-rich/#more-28492840&quot;&gt;Naval on Wealth&lt;/a&gt;:
This is more a series of blog posts and podcasts, which I started writing up key takeaways and action items from, but life got in the way. I may dive back into working on that again, or I may forget it. Either way, you should go read this entire series for yourself. Naval and team provide a lot of powerful takeaways to think about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Books&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, a few of these are older ones but they still hold a lot of wisdom in them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Principles - Ray Dalio: This is one of the grails for helping make better decisions. He walks through a lot of algorithms anyone can employ to help make better decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stumbling on Happiness - Daniel Gilbert: This is one I have had for a few years and never quite finished. But he walks through a lot of science behind happiness in people and why we are always wrong about what will make us most happy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Art of Gathering - Priya Parker: This is an excellent discussion about our current problems with meetings and really any other gathering. She walks through great strategies to help improve your future gatherings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Podcast&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not a huge podcast person, but I did listen to a couple recently that had a lot of good points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.madfientist.com/ramit-sethi-interview/&quot;&gt;Financial Independence&lt;/a&gt;:
The Mad Fientist is a great resource for really streamlining your tax efficiency strategies. This podcast episode he has a very solid conversationn with Ramit Sethi about FIRE and other aspects of saving and spending money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://podcasts.joerogan.net/podcasts/naval-ravikant&quot;&gt;The Joe Rogan Experience&lt;/a&gt;:
Normally, I’m not a Joe Rogan fan. But this episode with Naval was absolutely brilliant. Expanding on the series I posted in blogs, they do a deep dive on wealth creation in this episode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;That’s everything!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel like this is starting to get really long, so I’m going to wrap it up. Hopefully you check out some of these resources, if you do, please share how they have impacted you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Making Money isn't About Luck -- My Thoughts]]></title><description><![CDATA[This conversation discusses the concept and role of luck required to become wealthy. There is a common misconception that wealthy people…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/making-money-isnt-luck/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/making-money-isnt-luck/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;br&gt;
*Earlier this year [@naval](https://twitter.com/naval) posted a long tweetstorm about how to get rich without getting lucky, which blew up. Since then he has posted a series of podcasts expounding on each individual tweet (view it [here](https://nav.al/how-to-get-rich#more-28492840)). Each of these posts provided a more in depth look at what he meant. In this series of posts I will summarize what each podcast covers and write out some actionable take aways I plan on implementing from that particular conversation.*
&lt;p&gt;This conversation discusses the concept and role of luck required to become wealthy. There is a common misconception that wealthy people somehow lucked into their wealth, when really a majority of wealthy people got there by working really hard at some craft. Building something that created value for the rest of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naval highlights four types of luck that play different roles in how people can create wealth. The first, blind luck, is what people traditionally credit with making others wealthy. This is the lottery winner, some external event happens that I have no control over that makes me wealthy. Second, we have luck from hustling, where we are always moving, creating opportunities until the right opportunity hits. Third is luck from preparation, which is tied to being skilled in a field and being able to notice when a lucky break happens in that field. Finally there is luck from your unique character, which is weird. It is based on you building a unique character, brand or mindset where then luck finds you. I think the best way to summarize this one is this line “You created your own luck.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We cannot hope that luck will make us wealthy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We can build a skillset/product where we are in demand, which is a special type of luck.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wealth stacks up one chip at a time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Action Items&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this one, my main action item is to continue reading and working on my critical thinking and decision making skills. Along with my software engineering knowledge, eventually this will put me in position to do some incredible work.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Free Markets are Intrinsic to Humans -- My Thoughts]]></title><description><![CDATA[This entry covers the converstaion around free markets and how they are intrinsic to humans. One of the things I have found to be incredible…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/free-markets-are-intrinsic/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/free-markets-are-intrinsic/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;br&gt;
*Earlier this year [@naval](https://twitter.com/naval) posted a long tweetstorm about how to get rich without getting lucky, which blew up. Since then he has posted a series of podcasts expounding on each individual tweet (view it [here](https://nav.al/how-to-get-rich#more-28492840)). Each of these posts provided a more in depth look at what he meant. In this series of posts I will summarize what each podcast covers and write out some actionable take aways I plan on implementing from that particular conversation.*
&lt;p&gt;This entry covers the converstaion around free markets and how they are intrinsic to humans. One of the things I have found to be incredible with Naval is how he reframes ideas. This one in particular, I never thought about a conversation as being a value exchange. But he highlights how we as humans inherently track credits and debits, in the context of a conversation. If I am talking to you and feel like I am not getting enough value out of it, I will stop the conversation. He uses this as a parallel to how we operate in the free market. If you have a good or service I want, it will cost me some value to get that good or service. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also draws comparisons to organic systems, where there are parasites and symbiotes that come together to create a functioning system. Some organisms take nutrients and return a different form of that nutrient, while others just take and take and take. This part of the conversation shifted the focus to groups that despise wealth and want to redistribute it throughout society. They highlight what is happening in Venezuela as the epitome of a society that focused on redistributing wealth without incentivizing the creation of wealth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Humanity is the only species that keeps track of credits/debits.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;This inherent tracking is the same as free markets.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Action Items&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think, for me, the biggest action item I have from this one is just going to be focusing on bringing equal value to every transaction I participate in.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Make Abundance for the World - My Thoughts]]></title><description><![CDATA[Earlier this year @naval posted a long tweetstorm about how to get rich without getting lucky, which blew up. Since then he has posted a…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/create-abundance/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/create-abundance/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Earlier this year &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/naval&quot;&gt;@naval&lt;/a&gt; posted a long tweetstorm about how to get rich without getting lucky, which blew up. Since then he has posted a series of podcasts expounding on each individual tweet (view it &lt;a href=&quot;https://nav.al/how-to-get-rich#more-28492840&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Each of these posts provided a more in depth look at what he meant. In this series of posts I will summarize what each podcast covers and write out some actionable take aways I plan on implementing from that particular conversation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This converstaion was very interesting to me. As someone who grew up in a blue collar family, there was almost this taboo about wanting to be rich. There was this belief that rich people stole their wealth from someone else. Looking at wealth as a fixed quantity, not as something that can be increased across all of humanity. Naval highlights how this is an incorrect view of the economy, that in fact the economy can continue increasing in size as people start adding newer things of value to the overall system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wealth is not a zero sum game.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;True wealth creates abundance for the world.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we look at building wealth as adding new things of value to the world, we no longer have to think about how we can “trick” someone out of their money. We can instead start looking for holes that need to be filled. Anytime we think, “there should be a different way to do this,” we should instantly start ideating on that. Trying to identify why it is frustrating to us and how we can reduce or remove that frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Action Items&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, I think the paragraph above really sums up what my action item is going to be from this particular tweet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Look for pain points in life and try to solve them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Seek Wealth, Not Money or Status - My Thoughts]]></title><description><![CDATA[Earlier this year @naval posted a long tweetstorm about how to get rich without getting lucky, which blew up. Since then he has posted a…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/seek-wealth/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/seek-wealth/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Earlier this year &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/naval&quot;&gt;@naval&lt;/a&gt; posted a long tweetstorm about how to get rich without getting lucky, which blew up. Since then he has posted a series of podcasts expounding on each individual tweet (view it &lt;a href=&quot;https://nav.al/how-to-get-rich#more-28492840&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Each of these posts provided a more in depth look at what he meant. In this series of posts I will summarize what each podcast covers and write out some actionable take aways I plan on implementing from that particular conversation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first discussion is focused on differentiating between wealth, money and status. Often people tend to mix these three up and view them as interchangable. Obviously someone who attends high status social events will be wealthy and have a lot of money. Instead of just applying that blanket thought to all three, we should actually look at what each one really is. Naval provides a great definition for each of these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wealth is assets that earn while you sleep.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Money is how we transfer wealth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status is your rank in the social hierarchy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conversation around these concepts is very good and I would encourage you to listen to the full recording, it’s only six minutes long. But today I want to just highlight a few take aways I had and then provide a few ways I plan on putting these concepts into practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focus on creating wealth, instead of getting caught up in the typical status games people play. Status games are inherently zero-sum games which means there will be a winner and a loser. Focusing on these games will satisfy our baser instincts, but will rarely have material impacts on our ability to achieve freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money is a wealth transfer based on the time we put into something. When we create wealth for ourselves, we are buying back time to spend on things we are interested in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can classify a lot of the keeping up with the Joneses and FOMO spending as status seeking behavior. We all want the nice car or house to signal to the world we are doing “well” at the career/economic game.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Action Items&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build something of my own.&lt;/strong&gt; I have had an itch to create my own business for a while, but I never knew what to do. I need to make a leap and try something, even if it is a simple coaching side hustle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increase investment.&lt;/strong&gt; Over the past few years I have been slowly increasing the portion of my income I dedicate to investment. I need to ramp that up even more now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove status from my value equations.&lt;/strong&gt; It doesn’t matter what type of car I drive or what the size of my house/apartment is. I am not trying to be better than anyone else based on the material posessions I own.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Who is Jordan Ristow?]]></title><description><![CDATA[Allow me to reintroduce myself…Since I’ve revamped my site, I figured it would be a good idea to provide a bit more detail on who I am and…]]></description><link>https://jordanristow.com/about-me-post/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jordanristow.com/about-me-post/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2&gt;Allow me to reintroduce myself…&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I’ve revamped my site, I figured it would be a good idea to provide a bit more detail on who I am and what my story is (so far). Especially since right now the site is more focused on blogging than being my online portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Just the highlights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi, I’m Jordan! After being miserable with my life, I recently made a huge leap of faith, quit my old job, sold all of my belongings and moved to Austin Texas. I realized I needed focus on what would make me happy instead of worrying about other peoples expectations of me. So here I am, reinventing myself and enjoying life again. This blog is going to be my attempt at documenting my transition as well as an avenue to explore three of my favorite topics: software engineering, personal finance and philsophy/psychology.
Please tag along with me and reach out/connect with me if anything resonates with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Summary of Expertise:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Education Background&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BS in Materials Science and Engineering - Boise State University 12&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MS in Software Development - Maryville University 18&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Professional Background&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charles Schwab, Associate Software Engineer June 2019 -&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;United States Air Force, Operations Engineering Manager December 2016 - May 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;United States Air Force, Lead Project Manager August 2014 - December 2016&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;United States Air Force, Mechanical Engineer August 2013 - July 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;United States Air Force, Junior Engineer July 2012 - July 2013&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Technical Capabilities&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proficient with full stack development using Flask&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Object Oriented Programming with Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience with SciPy/NumPy and other data science libraries in Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ristowcapstoneproject.herokuapp.com/&quot;&gt;Sample website built with flask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Database Technologies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience with various SQL based databases (Postgres, MySQL, MicrosoftSQL)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience with MongoDB NoSQL databases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JavaScript&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience working with various JavaScript libraries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;React&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Node.js&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;D3.js&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Java&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding of Java OOP concepts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>